United States Strategic Bombing Survey: [Reports] (Pacific War)
Science, Technology & Business Division, Library of Congress
United States Strategic Bombing Survey: [Reports] (Pacific War) 1945-1947
D785.U63
109 reports
Science, Technology & Business Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
During World War II, the United States undertook massive aerial attacks against cities and industrial areas in the European and Pacific Theaters to destroy German and Japanese military forces. To study the effects of the bombing, the United States Strategic Bombing Survey (USSBS) was organized in November 1944. The USSBS was assigned two tasks: establish a basis for evaluating the importance and potential of air power as an instrument of military strategy; and, to plan the future development of the armed forces. The survey was originally conducted in Europe [European War reports]; the Pacific survey [Pacific War reports] was added after the surrender of Japan on August 15, 1945 by the order of President Harry S. Truman.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Online Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
Organizations
United States Strategic Bombing Survey.
Subjects
Air warfare.; World War, 1939-1945--Aerial operations.; World War, 1939-1945--Destruction and pillage.; World War, 1939-1945--Economic aspects--Japan.; World War, 1939-1945--Japan.; World War, 1939-1945--Pacific Ocean.
Titles
United States Strategic Bombing Survey (Series) (Pacific war)
Administrative Information
Provenance
Collection purchased by Library of Congress in 1969.
Access and Restrictions
Access to the collection is unrestricted.
Reports with LC call numbers can be requested from the Library's General Collections. Please note that some items may be held at offsite locations and may require additional time for retrieval.
Unclassed reports from the PB collection are available from the Technical Reports & Standards Unit, Science, Technology & Business Division. PB reports must be viewed in the Science Reading Room.
Additional Forms Available
United States Strategic Bombing Survey reports of the Pacific War are also available on microfilm in the Library's Microform & Electronic Resources Center as Microfilm 29945 (Catalog record: http://lccn.loc.gov/sn94094676). Copies may be ordered from the Photoduplication Service at the Library of Congress. Links have also been provided to digitized content, where known.
Related Material
Please note that 31 of the reports were reprinted in the publication United States Strategic Bombing Survey, a ten-volume series issued in 1976 by Garland Publishing, Inc. (Catalog record: http://lccn.loc.gov/75026396 ). Volumes 2-10 are in the Library's General Collections, under the LC call number D785.U57 1976.
The National Archives also holds records of the United States Strategic Bombing Survey (available at: http://www.archives.gov/research/guide-fed-records/groups/243.html).
Scope and Content Note
During World War II, the United States undertook massive aerial attacks against cities and industrial areas in the European and Pacific Theaters to destroy German and Japanese military forces. To study the effects of the bombing, the United States Strategic Bombing Survey (USSBS) was organized in November 1944. The USSBS was assigned two tasks: establish a basis for evaluating the importance and potential of air power as an instrument of military strategy; and, to plan the future development of the armed forces. The survey was originally conducted in Europe [European War reports]; the Pacific survey [Pacific War reports] was added after the surrender of Japan on August 15, 1945 by the order of President Harry S. Truman.
Arrangement of the Records
This collection is arranged in four series:
Office of the Chairman
Civilian Studies
Economic Studies
Military Studies
http://lccn.loc.gov/47024345
Container List
- Office of the Chairman (Reports 1-3)
  - Summary Report (Pacific War), Washington, D.C., 1 July 1946. Washington: U.S. Government Printing Office, 1946., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/46027723; iii, 32 p.: folded maps. (Report 1)
  - Japan's Struggle to End The War, Chairman's Office, 1 July 1946. [Washington]: Chairman's Office; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], 1946., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/46026977; v, 36 p.: tables. (Report 2)
  - The Effects of Atomic Bombs on Hiroshima and Nagasaki, Chairman's Office, 30 June 1946. Washington: Chairman's Office; [For sale by the] U.S. Government Printing Office, 1946., Catalog Records: http://lccn.loc.gov/46026779 and http://lccn.loc.gov/51021232; v, 46 p.: illus., maps (some folded). (Report 3)
- Civilian Studies (Reports 4-14)
  - Civilian Defense Division (Reports 4-11)
    - Field Report Covering Air Raid Protection and Allied Subjects, Tokyo, Japan. Dates of Field Team Survey: 19 November 1945-30 November 1945. [Washington]: Civilian Defense Division, March 1947., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2011655185; vi, 227 p.: illus., maps. (Report 4)
    - Field Report Covering Air-Raid Protection and Allied Subjects in Nagasaki, Japan. Dates of Field Team Survey: 11-16 November 1945. [Washington]: Civilian Defense Division, February 1947., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/med47002304; vi, 133 p.: illus., charts, map. (Report 5)
    - Field Report covering Air-Raid Protection and Allied Subjects in Kyoto, Japan. Dates of Survey: 4 November 1945-9 November 1945. [Washington]: Civilian Defense Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], February 1947., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/47032463; vi, 113 p.: illus., diagrams. (Report 6)
    - Field Report Covering Air-Raid Protection and Allied Subjects in Kobe, Japan. Dates of Survey: 29 October 1945-3 November 1945. [Washington]: Civilian Defense Division, February 1947., vi, 141 p.: illus., maps. (Report 7)
    - Field Report covering Air-Raid Protection and Allied Subjects in Osaka, Japan. Dates of Survey: 18 October 1945-28 October 1945. [Washington]: Civilian Defense Division, May 1947., vi, 150 p.: illus., maps, folded plates. (Report 8)
    - Target Report of Civilian Defense Division Field Team No. 1, Covering Air Raid Protection Facilities and Allied Subjects in the Town of Hiroshima, Japan. Dates of Field Team Survey: 10 October 1945-21 October 1945. [Washington]: Civilian Defense Division, 15 November 1945., [60] p.: illus.; Cover title: Hiroshima, Japan Field Report. (Civil Defense Report No. 1). (Report 9)
    - Summary Report, Covering Air-Raid Protection and Allied Subjects in Japan, 15 March 1946. [Washington]: Civilian Defense Division, 1946., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/47031652; iii, 19 p. (Report 10)
    - Final Report Covering Air Raid Protection and Allied Subjects in Japan. Dates of Survey: 1 October 1945-1 December 1945. [Washington]: Civilian Defense Division, February 1947., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/47032464; vii, 248 p.: illus., charts, maps (1 folded). (Report 11)
  - Medical Division (Reports 12-13)
    - The Effects of Bombing on Health and Medical Services in Japan. Dates of Survey: 24 October-31 November 1945. [Washington]: Medical Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], June 1947., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/med47002690; v, 253 p.: illus., tables, diagrams. (Report 12)
    - The Effects of Atomic Bombs on Health and Medical Services in Hiroshima and Nagasaki, March 1947. Washington: Medical Division; For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office, 1947., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/med47001002; ix, 91 p.: illus., tables, diagrams. (Report 13)
  - Morale Division (Report 14)
    - The Effects of Strategic Bombing on Japanese Morale, June 1947. [Washington]: Morale Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], 1947., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/84101632; vi, 262 p.: illus., tables. (Report 14)
- Economic Studies (Reports 15-60)
  - Aircraft Division (Reports 15-35)
    - The Japanese Aircraft Industry, May 1947. [Washington]: Aircraft Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], 1947., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/47031642; v, 173 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps. (Report 15)
    - Corporation Report, No. 1-20. [Washington]: Aircraft Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], 1945-1947., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/46027868; 20 v.: illus., maps (some folded). (Reports 16-35)
      - Mitsubishi Heavy Industries, Ltd. (Mitsubishi Jukogyo K K). Dates of Survey: 10 October 1945-29 November 1945. Corporation Report No. I (Airframes and Engines). [Washington]: Aircraft Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], June 1947., v, 343 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps (some folded). (Report 16)
      - Nakajima Aircraft Company, Ltd. (Nakajima Hikoki K K). Dates of Survey: October-November 1945. Corporation Report No. II (Airframes and Engines). [Washington]: Aircraft Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], June 1947., v, 190 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps (some folded). (Report 17)
      - Kawanishi Aircraft Co. (Kawanishi Kokuki Kabushiki Kaisha). Dates of Survey: 17 October-25 November 1945. Corporation Report No. III (Air Frames). [Washington]: Aircraft Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], April 1947., iii, 98 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps (some folded). (Report 18)
      - Kawasaki Aircraft Industries Company, Inc. (Kawasaki Kokuki Kogyo Kabushiki Kaisha). Dates of Survey: 10 October-29 November 1945. Corporation Report No. IV (Air Frames and Engines). [Washington]: Aircraft Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], May 1947., v, 63 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps (some folded). (Report 19)
      - Aichi Aircraft Company (Aichi Kokuki K K). Corporation Report No. V (Airframes and Engines). [Washington]: Aircraft Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], February 1947., v, 55 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps (some folded). (Report 20)
      - Sumitomo Metal Industries, Propeller Division (Sumitomo Kinzoku Kogyo K K, Puropera Seizosho). Dates of Survey: 20 October 1945-28 October 1945. Corporation Report No. VI (Propellors). [Washington]: Aircraft Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], December 1946., iv, 57 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps (some folded). (Report 21)
      - Hitachi Aircraft Company (Hitachi Kokuki KK). Date of Survey: November 1945. Corporation Report No. VII (Airframes and Engines). [Washington]: Aircraft Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], February 1947., v, 67 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps (some folded). (Report 22)
      - Japan International Air Industries, Ltd. (Nippon Kokusai Koku Kogyo KK). Dates of Survey: November 1945. Corporation Report No. VIII (Airframes). [Washington]: Aircraft Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], February 1945., iv, 15 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, map. (Report 23)
      - Japan Musical Instrument Manufacturing Company (Nippon Gakki Seizo K K). Date of Survey: 18 November 1945. Corporation Report No. IX (Propellors). [Washington]: Aircraft Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], 1 September 1946., iv, 27 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps (some folded). (Report 24)
      - Tachikawa Aircraft Company (Tachikawa Hikoki K K). Dates of Survey: 20-24 November 1945. Corporation Report No. X (Airframes). [Washington]: Aircraft Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], February 1947., v, 38 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps (some folded). (Report 25)
      - Fuji Airplane Company (Fuji Hikoki K K). Date of Survey: November 1945. Corporation Report No. XI (Airframes). [Washington]: Aircraft Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], 1 November 1946., v, 12 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps (some folded). (Report 26)
      - Showa Airplane Company (Showa Hikoki Kogyo K K). Dates of Survey: 17-18 October 1945. Corporation Report No. XII (Airframes). [Washington]: Aircraft Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], December 1946., v, 16 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, map. (Report 27)
      - Ishikawajima Aircraft Industries Company, Ltd. (Ishikawajima Koku Kogyo Kabushiki Kaisha). Dates of Survey: 26-27 November 1945. Corporation Report No. XIII (Engines). [Washington]: Aircraft Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], 1 November 1946., v, 23 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps. (Report 28)
      - Nippon Airplane Co. (Nippon Hikoki K K). Date of Survey: November 1945. Corporation Report No. XIV (Airframes). [Washington]: Aircraft Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], 1 September 1946., v, 22 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, map. (Report 29)
      - Kyushu Airplane Company (Kyushu Hikoki K K). Dates of Survey: 13-15 November 1945. Corporation Report No. XV (Airframes). [Washington]: Aircraft Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], February 1947., iv, 28 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps (one folded). (Report 30)
      - Shoda Engineering Company (Shoda Seisakujo). Date of Survey: 31 October 1945. Corporation Report No. XVI (Components). [Washington]: Aircraft Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], 1 September 1946., iv, 17 p.: illus., tables, diagrams. (Report 31)
      - Mitaka Aircraft Industries (Mitaka Koku Kogyo Kabushiki Kaisha). Date of Survey: 31 October 1945. Corporation Report No. XVII (Components). [Washington]: Aircraft Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], February 1947., iv, 19 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps. (Report 32)
      - Nissan Automobile Company (Nissan Jidosha K K). Dates of Survey: 24-25 November 1945. Corporation Report No. XVIII (Engines). [Washington]: Aircraft Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], 1 November 1946., v, 9 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps (one folded). (Report 33)
      - Army Air Arsenal and Navy Air Depots. Dates of Survey: 6 October-11 November 1945. Corporation Report No. XIX (Airframes and Engines). [Washington]: Aircraft Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], February 1947., iv, 68 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps (some folded). (Report 34)
      - Underground Production of Japanese Aircraft. Dates of Survey: 23 October-25 November 1945. Report No. XX. [Washington]: Aircraft Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], March 1947., iv, 71 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps (some folded). (Report 35)
  - Basic Materials Division (Report 36)
    - Coals and Metals in Japan's War Economy, April 1947. [Washington]: Basic Materials Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], 1947., Catalog Records: http://lccn.loc.gov/46032126 and http://lccn.loc.gov/47032126; v, 215 p.: illus., tables, diagrams. (Report 36)
  - Capital Goods, Equipment and Construction Division (Reports 37-39)
    - The Japanese Construction Industry. Dates of Survey: 4 October 1945 to 30 November 1945. Washington: Construction Section, Capital Equipment and Construction Branch; [For sale by the] U.S. Government Printing Office, 1946., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/47031651; vi, 47 p.: illus., tables. (Report 37)
    - Japanese Electrical Equipment. Dates of Survey: 4 October 1945 to 30 November 1945. Washington: Capital Equipment and Construction Division; [For sale by the] U.S. Government Printing Office, 1946., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/54041923; iv, 52 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, map. (Report 38)
    - The Japanese Machine Building Industry. Dates of Survey: 1 Oct. 1945-1 Dec. 1945. [Washington]: Capital Equipment and Construction Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], 15 November 1946., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/46027592; vii, 41, [1] p.: illus., tables, diagrams, map. (Report 39)
  - Electric Power Division (Reports 40-41)
    - The Electric Power Industry of Japan. Dates of Survey: 9 October 1945-3 December 1945. [Washington]: Electric Power Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office, 1946]., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/46027929; vii, 158 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps (some folded). (Report 40)
    - The Electric Power Industry of Japan (Plant Reports). Dates of Survey: 9 October-3 December 1945. [Washington]: Electric Power Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], May 1947., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/47046466; vi, 233 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps (some folded). (Report 41)
  - Manpower, Food and Civilian Supplies Division (Report 42)
    - The Japanese Wartime Standard of Living and Utilization of Manpower, January 1947. [Washington]: Manpower, Food and Civilian Supplies Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], 1947., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/47032979; xi, 146 p.: illus., tables, diagrams. (Report 42)
  - Military Supplies Division (Reports 43-48)
    - Japanese War Production Industries. Dates of Survey: October-November 1945. [Washington]: Military Supplies Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], 15 November 1946., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/47032981; iv, 23 p.: illus., tables. (Report 43)
    - Japanese Naval Ordnance. Dates of Survey: October-November 1945. [Washington]: Military Supplies Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], August 1946., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/47031643; v, 30 p.: illus., tables, diagram. (Report 44)
    - Japanese Army Ordnance. Dates of Survey: October-November 1945. [Washington]: Military Supplies Division, December 1946., iv, 31 p.: illus., tables, diagram. (Report 45)
    - Japanese Naval Shipbuilding. Dates of Survey: September-November 1945. [Washington]: Military Supplies Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], 15 November 1946., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/47032986; v, 24 p.: illus., tables, diagram. (Report 46)
    - Japanese Motor Vehicle Industry. Dates of Survey: October-November, 1945. [Washington]: Military Supplies Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], 1 November 1946., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/46027967; [ii], 16 p.: illus., tables. (Report 47)
    - Japanese Merchant Shipbuilding, January 1947. [Washington]: Military Supply Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], 1947., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/47032481; vi, 53 p.: illus., tables, diagrams. (Report 48)
  - Oil and Chemical Division (Reports 49-52)
    - Chemicals in Japan's War, February 1946. [Washington]: Oil and Chemical Division, 1946., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/51000053; 71 p.: illus., tables, maps. (Report 49)
    - Chemicals in Japan's War: Appendix to the Report. [Washington]: Oil and Chemical Division, [1946]., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/51000053; 251 p.: illus., tables, maps. (Report 50)
    - Oil in Japan's War, February 1946. [Washington]: Oil and Chemical Division, 1946., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/51015501; 133 p.: illus., tables, maps. (Report 51)
    - Oil in Japan's War: Appendix to the Report, February 1946. [Washington]: Oil and Chemical Division, 1946., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/51015501; 283 p.: illus., tables, maps. (Report 52)
  - Over-All Economic Effects Division (Report 53)
    - The Effects of Strategic Bombing on Japan's War Economy, December 1946. Washington: Over-All Economic Effects Division; [For sale by the] U.S. Government Printing Office, 1946., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/47032980; ix, 244 p.: illus., tables.; Includes Appendix A: U.S. Economic Intelligence on Japan–Analysis and Comparison; Appendix B: Gross National Product of Japan and Its Components; and Appendix C: Statistical Sources. (Report 53)
  - Transportation Division (Report 54)
    - The War Against Japanese Transportation, 1941-1945, May 1947. [Washington]: Transportation Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], 1947., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/48045693; 144 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps (some folded). (Report 54)
  - Urban Areas Division (Reports 55-60)
    - The Effects of Air Attack on Japanese Urban Economy: Summary Report, March 1947. [Washington]: Urban Areas Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], 1947., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/47032069; ix, 78 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps (some folded). (Report 55)
    - Effects of Air Attack on Urban Complex Tokyo-Kawasaki-Yokohama, June 1947. [Washington]: Urban Areas Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], 1947., vi, 64 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps (some folded). (Report 56)
    - The Effects of Air Attack on the City of Nagoya, June 1947. [Washington]: Urban Areas Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], 1947., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/47031634; v, 89 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps (some folded). (Report 57)
    - Effects of Air Attack on Osaka-Kobe-Kyoto. Dates of Survey: November-December 1945. [Washington]: Urban Areas Division; [For sale by the U.S. Government Printing Office], June 1947., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/47046467; vi, 275 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps (some folded). (Report 58)
    - The Effects of Air Attack on the City of Nagasaki. Dates of Survey: 15 November-1 December 1945. [Washington]: Urban Areas Division, April 1947., v, 53 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps. (Report 59)
    - Effects of Air Attack on the City of Hiroshima, June 1947. [Washington]: Urban Areas Division, 1947., Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/59040289; v, 57 p.: illus., tables, maps (one folded). (Report 60)
- Military Studies (Reports 61-108)
  - Military Analysis Division (Reports 61-71a)
    - Air Forces Allied with the United States in the War Against Japan, February 1947. [Washington]: Military Analysis Division, 1947., iv, 19 p.: illus., tables. (Report 61)
    - Japanese Air Power, July 1946. [Washington]: Military Analysis Division, 1946., viii, 83 p.: illus., maps, diagrams, tables (some folded). (Report 62)
    - Japanese Air Weapons and Tactics, January 1947. [Washington]: Military Analysis Division, 1947., vi, 76 p.: illus., maps, diagrams, tables. (Report 63)
    - The Effect of Air Action on Japanese Ground Army Logistics. Dates of survey, 11 October 1945 to 15 February 1946. [Washington]: Military Analysis Division, April 1947., vii, 192 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps (some folded). (Report 64)
    - Employment of Forces Under the Southwest Pacific Command, February 1947. [Washington]: Military Analysis Division, 1947., v, 65 p.: illus., folded diagram. (Report 65)
    - The Strategic Air Operation of Very Heavy Bombardment in the War Against Japan (Twentieth Air Force): Final Report. Dates of Survey: 10 October 1945-29 November 1945. Washington: Military Analysis Division, Army and Army Air Section; [For sale by the] U.S. Government Printing Office, 1 September 1946., vi, 39 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps. (Report 66)
    - Air Operations in China, Burma, India - World War II. Dates of Survey: 1 July 1946. [Washington]: Military Analysis Division, March 1947., v, 107 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps (some folded). (Report 67)
    - The Air Transport Command in the War Against Japan, December 1946. [Washington]: Military Analysis Division, 1946., v, 18 p.: illus., tables, maps (some folded). (Report 68)
    - The Thirteenth Air Force in the War Against Japan, 30 September 1946. [Washington]: Military Analysis Division, 1946., v, 25 p.: illus., tables, diagrams, maps (some folded). (Report 69)